<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A right pithy, pleasant, and merry comedy, entituled, Gammer Gurton's needle made by Mr. S. ...</title>
            <title>Gammer Gurton's needle</title>
            <author>S., Mr., Mr. of Art.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11845813</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11845813</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49842</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61493)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49842)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 550:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A right pithy, pleasant, and merry comedy, entituled, Gammer Gurton's needle made by Mr. S. ...</title>
                  <title>Gammer Gurton's needle</title>
                  <author>S., Mr., Mr. of Art.</author>
                  <author>Stevenson, William, d. 1575.</author>
                  <author>Bridges, John, d. 1618.</author>
                  <author>Still, John, 1543?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Johnson, and are to be sold by Nath. Brook ..., Francis Kirkman ..., Tho. Johnson ..., Henry Marsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Played on the stage near a hundred years ago in Christs College in Cambridge."</note>
                  <note>Formerly ascribed to John Still, Bishop of Bath and Wells, or to John Bridges, Bishop of Oxford, but now attributed to William Stevenson of Christ's college, Cambridge. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49842:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49842:1"/>
            <p>A Right Pithy, Pleaſant, and Merry COMEDY, ENTITULED, <hi>Gammer Gurtons Needle;</hi> Played on the Stage near a hundred years ago in <hi>Chriſts-Colledge</hi> in CAMBRIDGE.</p>
            <p>Made by <hi>Mr. S.</hi> Maſter of Art.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Johnſon,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Nath. Brook</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhil, Francis Kirkman</hi> at the <hi>John Fletchers Head,</hi> on the Back-ſide of St. <hi>Clements, Tho. Johnſon</hi> at the Golden Key in Pauls-Church-yard, and <hi>Henry Marſh</hi> at the Princes Arms in Chancery-lane, near <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:49842:2"/>
            <head>The Names of the SPEAKERS i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>y.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>DIccoon</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſervant.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Gam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>Gurtons</hi> Maid.</l>
               <l>Gammer <hi>Gurton.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cock,</hi> Gammer <hi>Gurtons</hi> Boy.</l>
               <l>Dame <hi>Chat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doctor <hi>Rat,</hi> the Curate.</l>
               <l>Mayſter <hi>Baily.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Doll,</hi> Dame <hi>Chats</hi> Mayd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scapethryft,</hi> Mayſter <hi>Bailyes</hi> ſervant.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>MUTES.</p>
            <closer>God ſave the KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <div type="prologue">
               <pb facs="tcp:49842:2"/>
               <head>The PROLOGUE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>As Gammer Gurton, with many a wide ſtiche,</l>
                  <l>Sat peſing and patching of Hodge her mans briche.</l>
                  <l>By chance or misfortune as ſhe her gear toſt,</l>
                  <l>In Hodge lether briches her nedle ſhe loſt.</l>
                  <l>When Diccon the bedlam had hard by report,</l>
                  <l>That good Gammer Gurton was rob'd in this ſort,</l>
                  <l>He quietlie perſwaded with her in that ſtound,</l>
                  <l>Dame Chat her dear goſſip this nedle had found.</l>
                  <l>Yet knew ſhe no more of this matter (alas)</l>
                  <l>Then knoweth Tom our clarke what the Prieſt ſaith at maſſe.</l>
                  <l>Hereof there enſued ſo fearfull a fray,</l>
                  <l>Mas Doctor was ſent for theſe goſſips to ſtay;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he was Curate, and eſteemed full wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Who found that he ſought not by Diccons device,</l>
                  <l>When all things were tombled and clean out of faſſion,</l>
                  <l>Whether it were by fortune, or ſome other conſtellation,</l>
                  <l>Sodenlie the nedle Hodge found by the pricking,</l>
                  <l>And drew out of his buttocke where he found it ſticking.</l>
                  <l>Their hearts then at reſt with perfect ſecurity.</l>
                  <l>With a pot of good nale they ſtroak up their plaudity.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>The firſt Act.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>The firſt Scean.</head>
                  <stage>Diccon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MAny a mile have I walked, divers and ſundry waies,</l>
                        <l>And many a good mans houſe have bin at in my days.</l>
                        <l>Many a goſſips cup in my time have I taſted,</l>
                        <l>And many a broche ſpite, have I both turned and baſted.</l>
                        <l>Many a peece of bacon have I had out of their balkes,</l>
                        <l>In running over the country, with and long wery walkes.</l>
                        <l>Yet came my foot never, within thoſe door cheekes,</l>
                        <l>To ſeek Fleſh or Fiſh, Garlike, Onions or Leekes,</l>
                        <l>That ever I ſaw a ſort in ſuch a plight,</l>
                        <l>As here within this houſe appeareth to my ſight,</l>
                        <l>There is howling and ſcowling, all caſt in a dumpe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:3"/>With whewling and pewling, as though they had loſt a trump.</l>
                        <l>Sighing and ſobbing, they weep and they wail.</l>
                        <l>I marvel in my mind, what the devil they ail,</l>
                        <l>The old trot ſits groning, with alas and alas,</l>
                        <l>And Lib wrings her hands, and takes on in worſe caſe.</l>
                        <l>With poor Cocke their boy, they be driven in ſuch fits,</l>
                        <l>I fear me the folkes be not well in their wits.</l>
                        <l>Ask them what they ail, or who brought them in this ſtay?</l>
                        <l>They anſwer not at all, but alacke and welaway,</l>
                        <l>When I ſaw it booted not, out at doors I hied me,</l>
                        <l>And caught a ſlip of Bacon, when I ſaw that none ſpied me,</l>
                        <l>Which I intended not far hence, unles my purpoſe fail,</l>
                        <l>Shall ſerve for a ſhoinghorn to draw on two pots of ale.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>The firſt Acte.</head>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>The ſecond Sceane</head>
                  <stage>Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SE ſo cham arayed with dabling in the durt;</l>
                        <l>She that ſet me to ditching, ich wold ſhe had the ſqurt.</l>
                        <l>Was never poor ſoul that ſuch a life had?</l>
                        <l>Gogs bones this vilthy glay haſe dreſt me too bad,</l>
                        <l>Gods ſoul, ſee how this ſtuffe tears,</l>
                        <l>Ich were better to be a Bareward and ſet to keep Bares.</l>
                        <l>By the maſſe here is a gasſhe, a ſhamefull hole indead,</l>
                        <l>And one ſtitch tear furder, a man may thruſt in his head.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By my fathers ſoul Hodge, if I ſhuld now beſworn,</l>
                        <l>I cannot chuſe but ſay thy breech is foul betorn.</l>
                        <l>But the next remedy in ſuch a caſe and hap,</l>
                        <l>Is to plaunche on a piece, as brod as thy cap.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hogd.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs ſoul man, tis not yet two daies fully ended,</l>
                        <l>Since my dame Gurton (cham ſure) theſe breches amended</l>
                        <l>But cham made ſuth a drudge to trudge at every need,</l>
                        <l>Chwold rend it though it were ſtitched what ſturdy packhreed</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hodge, let thy breeches go, and ſpeak and tell me ſoon,</l>
                        <l>What devil aileth gammer gurton, &amp; Lib her maid to frown.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tuſh man thart deceived, tis their daily looke,</l>
                        <l>They cover ſo over y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coles, their eies be bleard with ſmooke.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay by the maſſe, I perfectly perceived as I came hether.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:3"/>That either Tib and her dame hath been by the ears together,</l>
                        <l>Or els as great a matter as thou ſhalt ſhortly ſee.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Now ich beſeech our Lord they never better agree.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By gogs ſoul there they ſit as ſtill as ſtones in the ſtreet</l>
                        <l>As though they had been taken with ſome fairies, or els w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome ill ſpreet</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs hart, I durſt have laid my cap to a crown,</l>
                        <l>Chwould learn of ſome prancome as ſoon as ich cham to town.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Hodge art thou inſpired? or didſt thou thereof here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay, but ich ſaw ſuch a wounder as ich ſaw not this vii year,</l>
                        <l>Tome Tankards Cow (he gogs bones) ſhe ſet me up her ſail,</l>
                        <l>And Hinging about his halfe aker fisking with her tail;</l>
                        <l>As though there had been in her arſe a ſwarm of Bees,</l>
                        <l>And chad not cryed tphrowh hoor, ſhead lept out of his Lees,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Hodge lies the conning in Tom tankards cowes tail?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Well ich chaue hard ſome ſay ſuch tokens do not fail,</l>
                        <l>But caſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not tell in faith Diccon, why ſhe frowns, or wherat?</l>
                        <l>Hath no man ſtoln her Ducks or Hens, or gelded gib her Cat?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What devil can I tell man, I cold not have one word,</l>
                        <l>They gave no more heed to my talke then thou woldſt to a lord.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ich cannot ſtill but muſe, what mervailous thing it is,</l>
                        <l>Chill in and know my ſelfe, what matters are amiſe,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then fare well hodge a while, ſince thou doeſt inward haſt,</l>
                        <l>For I will into the good wife Chats, to feel how the ale doth taſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>The fiſt Acte.</head>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>The third Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Hodge. Lib.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hog.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cham agaſt by the maſſe, ich wot not what to do,</l>
                        <l>Chad need bleſſe me well before ich go them to.</l>
                        <l>Perchaunce ſome fellon ſpirit may haunt our houſe indeed,</l>
                        <l>And then chwere but at noddy to venter cha no need.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cham worſe then mad by the maſſe to be at this ſtay.</l>
                        <l>Cham chib, cham blamd, and beaten all thours on the day.</l>
                        <l>Lamed and hunder ſtorved, pricked up all in Jagges,</l>
                        <l>Having no patch to hide my backe, ſave a few rotten ragges.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I ſay Tib, if thou be Tib, as I trow ſure thou be,</l>
                        <l>What devil make a do is this, between our dame and thee?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs bread Hodge thou had a good turn thou wart not here this while.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:4"/>It had ben better for ſome of us to have ben hence a mile.</l>
                        <l>My Gammer is ſo out of courſe, and frantike all at ones,</l>
                        <l>That Cocke our boy, &amp; I poor wench, have felt it on our bones.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the matter, ſay on Tib whereat ſhe taketh ſo on?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>She is undone ſhe ſaith (alas,) her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oy and life is gone.</l>
                        <l>If ſhe here not of ſome comfort, ſhe is ſaith but dead,</l>
                        <l>Shall never come within her lips, on inch of meat ne bread.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Bir Ladie cham not very glad, to ſee her in this dumpe,</l>
                        <l>Chold a noble her ſtole hath fallen, &amp; ſhe hath broke her rumpe</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay and that were the worſt, we wold not greatly care,</l>
                        <l>For burſting of her huckle bone, or breaking of her Chair.</l>
                        <l>But greater, greater, is her grief, as hodge we ſhall all féel.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Gogs wounds Tib, my gammer has never loſt her Néele?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Her Néele?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Her néele?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Her neele hy him that made me, it is true Hodge I tell thee,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs ſacrament, I would ſhe had loſt tharte out of her belly.</l>
                        <l>The Devil or els his dame, they ought her ſure a ſhame,</l>
                        <l>How a murrion came this chaunce, (ſay Tib) unto our dame?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſat her down on the pes, and bad me reach thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</l>
                        <l>And by &amp; by, a vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in it, or ſhe had take two ſtitches</l>
                        <l>To clout upon thine ars, by chaunce aſide ſhe lears,</l>
                        <l>And gib our cat in the milk pan, ſhe ſpied over head and ears.</l>
                        <l>A hoor, out theef, ſhe cried aloud, and ſwapt the breeches down,</l>
                        <l>Up went her ſtaffe, and out leapt gib at doors into the town.</l>
                        <l>And ſince that time was never wight cold ſet their eies upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it,</l>
                        <l>Gogs maliſon chaue Cocke and I, bid twentie times light on it</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod</speaker>
                     <p>And is not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my breches ſewid up, to morrow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>I</hi> ſhuld wear</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>No in faith hodge thy breches lie, for all this never the near</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now a ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance light on al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſort, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> better ſhold have kept it,</l>
                        <l>The cat, the houſe, and tib our maid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> better ſhold have ſwep it</l>
                        <l>Se where ſhe cometh crawling, come on in twenty devils way</l>
                        <l>Ye have made a fair daies worke, have you not? pray you ſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>The firſt Act.</head>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>The iiii. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Gammer. Hodge. Tib Cocke.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>ALas, alas, I may will curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> ban,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:49842:4"/>
                        <l>This day that ever I ſaw it, with gib and the milke pan.</l>
                        <l>For theſe and ill lucke together, as knoweth Cock my boie,</l>
                        <l>Have ſtacke away my dear neele, and robd me of my joie.</l>
                        <l>My fair long ſtraight néele that was mine onely treaſure,</l>
                        <l>The firſt day of my ſorrow is, and laſt of my pleaſure.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Might ha kept it when ye had it, but fools will be fools ſtill,</l>
                        <l>Loſe that is vaſt in your hands, ye need not but ye will.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Go hie thee tib, and run thou hoor, to thend here of the town</l>
                        <l>Didſt cary out duſt in thy lap, ſeek where thou poreſt it down,</l>
                        <l>And as thou ſaweſt me roking, in the aſhes where I morned,</l>
                        <l>So ſee in all the heap of duſt, thou leave no ſtraw unturned.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib</speaker>
                     <p>That chal gammer ſwithe and tite, and ſone be here again,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Tib ſtoop &amp; loke down to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground to it, and take ſome pain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Here is a prety matter, to ſee this gere how it goes,</l>
                        <l>By gogs ſoul I think you wold loes your arſe, and it were looſe.</l>
                        <l>Your néele loſt, it is pitie you ſhold lack care and endles ſorrow</l>
                        <l>Gogs deth how ſhall my breches be ſewid, ſhall I go thus to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ah hodge, hodg, if that ich cold find my néele by the reed</l>
                        <l>Chould ſow thy breches ich promiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o full good double threed</l>
                        <l>And ſet a patch on either knee, ſhull laſt this months twain,</l>
                        <l>Now god and Saint Sithe I pray, to ſend it home again.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Whereto ſerved your hands &amp; eies, but your neele to keep,</l>
                        <l>What devil had you els to do, ye keep ich wot no ſheep.</l>
                        <l>Cham fain abrode to dig and delve, in water, mire and clay,</l>
                        <l>Soſſing and poſſing in the durt, ſtill from daie to daie.</l>
                        <l>A hundred things that be abrod, cham ſet to ſee them weel,</l>
                        <l>And four of you ſit idle at home, and cannot keep a néele.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My néele alas ich loſt hodge, what time ich me up haſted,</l>
                        <l>To ſave milke ſet up for the, which gib our cat hath waſted.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The devil he burſt both gib, and Tib, with all the reſt,</l>
                        <l>Cham alwaies ſure of the worſt end, who ever have the beſt.</l>
                        <l>Where ha you ben fidging abrod, ſince you your néele loſt?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Within the houſe, and at the door, ſitting by this ſame poſt.</l>
                        <l>Where I was looking a long hour, before theſe folke came here,</l>
                        <l>But welawaie, all was in vain, my néele is never the near:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Set me a candle, let me ſeek, and grope where ever it be,</l>
                        <l>Gogs hart ye be foolliſh (ich think) you know it not when you it ſee</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Come hether Cocke, what Cocke I ſay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <p>How Gammer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:5"/>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Go hie thee ſoon, and grope behind the old broſſe pan,</l>
                        <l>Which thing when thou haſt done.</l>
                        <l>There ſhalt thou find an old ſhoo, wherein if thou looke well,</l>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt find lieng an inche of white tallow candell,</l>
                        <l>Light it, and bring it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>te away,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſhalbe done anone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay tary hodge till thou haſt light, and then weel ſeek ich one</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Cum away ye horſon boy, are yeaſleep? ye muſt have a crier</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <p>Ich cannot get the candle light, here is almoſt no fire</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chil hold the peny, chil make y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come if ich may catch thine ears</l>
                        <l>Art deffe thou horſon boy? cocke <hi>I</hi> ſay, why canſt not heares;</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Beat him not Hodge but helpe the boy and come you two together.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>The i. Acte.</head>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>The v. Sceane</head>
                  <stage>Gammer. Tib. Chocke. Hodge.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>HOw now Tib, quick lets here, what news thou haſt brought hether?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chaue toſt and tumbled yonder heap our and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ver again,</l>
                        <l>And winowed it through my fingers, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold winow grain</l>
                        <l>Not ſo much as a hens turd but in pieces I tare it,</l>
                        <l>Or what ſo ever cold or clay I foomd, I did not ſpare it.</l>
                        <l>Looking within and eke without, to find your neele (alas)</l>
                        <l>But all in vain and without help, you neele is where it was.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas my neele we ſhall never meet, adue, adue for aye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo gammer, we might it finde if we knew where it lay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs croſs Gammer, if ye will laugh look in but at the door,</l>
                        <l>And ſee how Hodg lieth tomblinge and toſſing amids the floure</l>
                        <l>Raking there ſome faire to find among the aſhes dead</l>
                        <l>Where there is not one ſparke, ſo big as a pins head,</l>
                        <l>At laſt in a dark corner two ſparkes he thought he ſees</l>
                        <l>Which where indede nought els, but Gib our cats two eyes</l>
                        <l>Puffe quod hodg thinking thereby to have fyre without doubt,</l>
                        <l>With that Gib ſhut her two eyes, and ſo the fyre was out</l>
                        <l>And by and by them opened, even as they were before,</l>
                        <l>With that the ſparkes appered even as they had done of yore,</l>
                        <l>And even as hodg blew the fire as he did thinck</l>
                        <l>Gibas ſhe felt the blaſt ſtraight way began to wincke,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:5"/>Till Hodge fell of ſwering, as came beſt to his turn,</l>
                        <l>The fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r was ſure bewicht, and therefore would not burn:</l>
                        <l>At laſt Gib up the ſtayers, among the old poſtes and pins,</l>
                        <l>And hodge he hied him after til broke were both his ſhins:</l>
                        <l>Curſing and ſwearing oths, were never of his making,</l>
                        <l>That Gib would fire the houſe, if that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he were not taken,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>See here is all the thought that the fooliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rohin taketh.</l>
                        <l>And Tib me think at his elbow almoſt as mery maketh</l>
                        <l>This is all the wit ye have when others make their mone,</l>
                        <l>Come down Hodge, where art thou? and let the Cat alone,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs heart, help and come up, Gib in her taile hath fire,</l>
                        <l>And is like to burn all if the get a little hier:</l>
                        <l>Cum down (quoth you,) nay then you might count me a patch</l>
                        <l>The houſe cometh down on your heads if it take ons y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thatch</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the cats eyes fool that ſhineth in the dark.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Hath the Cat do you think in every eye a ſpark?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>No, but they ſhine as like fire as ever man ſée.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>By the maſs and ſhe burn all, youſh bear the blame for me</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cum down and help to ſéek here our neel that it were found</l>
                        <l>Down Tib on thy knées I ſay, down Cock to the ground,</l>
                        <l>To God I make a vow, and ſo to good Saint Anne</l>
                        <l>A candel ſhall they have a péece, get it where I can,</l>
                        <l>If I may my neel finde in one place or in other.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now a vengeaunce on gib light, on gib and gibs mother</l>
                        <l>And all the generacion of Cats both far and ne're</l>
                        <l>Look on the ground horſon thinks thou the néel is here.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By my trouth gammar me thought your nedle here I ſaw</l>
                        <l>But when my fingers toucht it, I felt it was a ſtraw,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>See Hodge what 'tis, may it not be within it,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Break it ſool with thy hand, and ſée, &amp; thou canſt finde it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay break it you Hodge according to your word.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs ſides, fie it ſtinck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>: it is a Cats tourd,</l>
                        <l>It were well done to make thée eat it by the maſs.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This matter amendeth not my néel is ſtill where it waſs</l>
                        <l>Our candle is at an end let us all in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uight</l>
                        <l>And come another time, when we have more light.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:49842:6"/>
               <head>The ii Acte.</head>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>Firſt a Song.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Back and ſide go bare, go bare, booth foot and hand go colde:</l>
                     <l>But Belly god ſend thée good Ale ynoughe, whether it be new or old.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I Can not eat, but little meat, my ſtomack is not good:</l>
                     <l>But ſure I think, that I can drink with him that weares a hood.</l>
                     <l>Though I go bare, take ye no care, I am nothing a colde:</l>
                     <l>I ſtuffe my skin, ſo full within, of joly good Ale and old.</l>
                     <l>Back and ſide, go bare, go bare, booth foot and hand go cold:</l>
                     <l>But belly god ſend the good Ale inoughe whether it be new or old.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I love no roſt, but a nut brown toſte, and a Crab laid in the fire,</l>
                     <l>A little bread, ſhall do me ſtead much bread I not deſire:</l>
                     <l>No froſte nor ſnow, no winde I trow can hurte mee if I wolde,</l>
                     <l>I am ſo wrapt, and throwly lapt of joly good Ale and old.</l>
                     <l>Back and ſide go bare, &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And Tib my wife, that as her life loveth well good Ale to ſéek,</l>
                     <l>Full ofte drinkes ſhée, till ye may ſée the teares run down her chéekes:</l>
                     <l>Then dooth ſhe trowle, to me the bowle even as a mault worm ſhuld,</l>
                     <l>And ſaith ſwéet heart, I took my part of this joly good Ale and old.</l>
                     <l>Back and ſide go bare, &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:6"/>
                     <l>Now let them drink, till they nod and wink, even as good fellows ſhould do</l>
                     <l>They ſhall not miſs, to have the bliſſe, good Ale doth bring men to:</l>
                     <l>And all poor ſouls that have ſcow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed boules or have them luſtely trolde,</l>
                     <l>God ſave the lives, of them and their wives whether they be yong or old.</l>
                     <l>Back and ſide go bare, &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>The firſt Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Diccon. Hodg.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WElldone by Gogs malt, wellſong and wellſaid,</l>
                        <l>Come on mother Chat as thou art true maid.</l>
                        <l>One freſh pot of Ale lets ſée to make an end</l>
                        <l>Againſt this cold wether, my naked armes to defend</l>
                        <l>This gere it warms the ſoul, now wind blow on the worſt,</l>
                        <l>And let us drink and ſwill, till that our bellies burſte</l>
                        <l>Now were he a wiſe man, by cunning cold define</l>
                        <l>Which way my journey lyeth, or where Diccon will dine</l>
                        <l>But one good turn I have, be it by night or day</l>
                        <l>South, Eaſt, North or Weſt, I am never out of my way.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chym goodly rewarded, cham I not, do you thincke?</l>
                        <l>Chad a goodly dinner for all my ſweat and ſwincke,</l>
                        <l>Neither Butter, Chéeſe, Milk, Onyons, Fleſh nor Fiſh,</l>
                        <l>Save this poor pece of barly bread, tis a pleaſant coſtly diſh.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hail fellow Hodg, &amp; will to fare, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy meat, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> have any?</l>
                        <l>But by thy words as I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmeled; thy daintrels be not many</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Daintrels dicco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (gogs ſoul ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ſave this pece of dry horsbred</l>
                        <l>Cha byt no bit this live long day, no crome come in my hed</l>
                        <l>My guts they yawle, crawle, and all my belly rumbleth,</l>
                        <l>The puddings cannot lie ſtill, ech one over other tumbleth</l>
                        <l>By gogs hart cham ſo vexte, and in my belly pend</l>
                        <l>Chould one péece were at the ſpitlehouſe another at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtels end.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Why hodg, was there none at home thy dinner for to ſet?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Godgs bread dicco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ich came to late, was nothing therto get</l>
                        <l>Gib (a fowl feind might on her light) lickt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> milk pan ſo clen</l>
                        <l>Sée diccon, 'twas not ſo wel waſht this vii. yere as ich wene</l>
                        <l>A peſtilence light on al ill luck, chad thought yet for all this</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:7"/>Of a morſel of bacon behind the dore at worſt ſhould not miſs,</l>
                        <l>But when ich ſought a ſlip to cut, as ich was wont to do</l>
                        <l>Gogs ſouls Diccon, gib our Cat had eat the bacon to.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Which bacon Diccon ſtole, as is declared before.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ill luck quod he, maiy ſwere it hodg, this day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth to tell</l>
                        <l>Thou roſe not on thy right ſide, or elſe bleſt thée not well,</l>
                        <l>Thy milk ſlopt up, thy baco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filtched, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was to bad luck hodg.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay, nay, there was a fowler fault, my ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ga me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bodg</l>
                        <l>Séeſt not how cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rent &amp; torn, my héels, my knees &amp; my bréech</l>
                        <l>Chad thought as ich ſat by the fire, help here &amp; there a ſtitch</l>
                        <l>But there ich was powpte indéed,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Hodg?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Bootes not man to tell,</l>
                        <l>Cham ſo dreſt amonſt a ſort of fooles, chad better be in hell,</l>
                        <l>My ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mar (cham aſhamed to ſay) by god ſerbed me not wéel.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſo Hodg?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg</speaker>
                     <p>Haſe ſhe not gone troweſt now and loſt ber néele.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Her Eele Hodg, who fiſht of late? that was a dainty diſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tuſh, tuſh, her néele, her néele, her néele man. tys neither fleſh nor fiſh.</l>
                        <l>A lytle thing with an hole in the end, as bright as any ſyller,</l>
                        <l>Small, long, ſharp at the point, &amp; ſtraight as any piller.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not what a devil y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſt, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bringſt me more in doubt</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Knoweſt not what tom tailers man ſits broching through a clout</l>
                        <l>A neele, néele, a neele, my gammers neele is gone.</l>
                        <l>Her néele Hodg, now I ſmell thée, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was a chaunce alone,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſs y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hadſt a ſhameful loſs, &amp; it wer but for thy brcehes</l>
                        <l>Gogs ſoul man chould give a crown chad it but iii. ſtitches.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſayeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> Hodg, what ſhuld he have, again thy nedle got</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Bem vathers ſoul, and chad it chould give him a new grot.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Canſt thou kéep counſaile in this caſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Els chwold my thong were out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Do than but then by my adviſe. &amp; I wil fetch it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doubt,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Chyll run, chyll ride, chyll dygge, chyll delue, chill toyle, chill trudge ſhalt ſée:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chill hold, chill draw, chill pull, chill pynch chill knéel on my bare knée.</l>
                        <l>Chill ſcrape, chill ſcratch, chill ſyfte, chill ſéek, chill bow, chill bend, chill ſweat.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:7"/>Chil ſtoop, chil ſtur, chil cap, chil knele, chil crep on ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds &amp; féet,</l>
                        <l>Chil be thy bondman Diccon, ich ſwear by Sun and Moon</l>
                        <l>And channot ſum what to ſtop this gap, cham utterly undone </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Pointing behind to his torn breeches.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, is ther any ſpecial cauſs, thou takeſt hereat ſuch ſorow</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Kirſtian Clack Tom ſimſons maid, by the maſs come hether to morow</l>
                        <l>Chamnot able to ſay, betwéen us what may hap,</l>
                        <l>She ſmiled on me the laſt ſunday when ich put off my cap,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Wel Hodg this is a matter of weight, &amp; muſt be kept cloſe,</l>
                        <l>It might els turn to both our coſtes as the world now goſe,</l>
                        <l>Shalt ſware to be no blab Hodg.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Chill Diccon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then go to,</l>
                        <l>Lay thine hand here, ſay after me as thou ſhalt here me do.</l>
                        <l>Haſte no book?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Cha no book I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then néeds muſt force us both,</l>
                        <l>Upon my bréech to lay thine hand, &amp; there to take thine oth.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I Hodg bréecheleſs,</l>
                        <l>Swear to Diccon recheleſs</l>
                        <l>By the croſs that I ſhall kiſs,</l>
                        <l>To kéep his counſaile cloſe</l>
                        <l>And always me to diſpoſe</l>
                        <l>To work that his pleaſure is. </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Here he kiſſeth Diccons bréech.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now Hodg ſée thou take héed</l>
                        <l>And do as I thée bid</l>
                        <l>For ſo I judge it méet,</l>
                        <l>This nedle again to win</l>
                        <l>There is no ſhift therein</l>
                        <l>But conjure up a ſpréet,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>What the great devil Diccon I ſay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea in good faith, that is the way.</l>
                        <l>Fet with ſome prety charm.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Soft Diccon be not to haſty yet,</l>
                        <l>By the maſs for ich begin to ſweat,</l>
                        <l>Cham afraid of ſome harm,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come hether then and ſtur the nat</l>
                        <l>One inche out of this Cyrcle plat</l>
                        <l>But ſtand as I thée teach.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:8"/>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſhall ich be here ſafe from their clawes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The mayſter devil with his longe pawes</l>
                        <l>Here to thée cannot reache:</l>
                        <l>Now will I ſettle me to this geare.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I ſay Diccon,, hear me, hear:</l>
                        <l>Go ſoftely to this matter.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>What devil man, art afraide of nought</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Canſt not tarry a little thought</l>
                        <l>Till ich make a curte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>e of water.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand ſtill to it, why ſhuldeſt thou fear him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs ſides Diccon, me think ich hear him</l>
                        <l>And tarry chal mare all.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>The matter is no worſe then I told it,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By the maſſe cham able no longer to hold it,</l>
                        <l>To bad iche muſt beraye the hall,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Stand to it Hodg, ſture not you horſon.</l>
                        <l>What devil, be thine ars ſtringes bruſten?</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelf a while but ſtay,</l>
                        <l>The devil I ſmell him will be here anone.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hold him faſt Diccon, cham gone, cham gone</l>
                        <l>Chil not be at that fraye.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>The ii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>The ii. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Diccon Chat.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>FY ſhitten knave, and out upon thee</l>
                        <l>A bove all other loutes fie on thée,</l>
                        <l>Is not here a clenly prancke?</l>
                        <l>But thy matter was no better</l>
                        <l>Nor thy preſence here no ſweter,</l>
                        <l>To flye I can thee thank:</l>
                        <l>Here is a matter worthy gloſing</l>
                        <l>Of Gammer Gurtons Nedle loſing</l>
                        <l>And a foul péece of wark,</l>
                        <l>A man I thincke might make a play</l>
                        <l>And nede no word to this they ſay</l>
                        <l>Being but halfe a Clark.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:8"/>Soft, let me alone, I will take the charge</l>
                        <l>This matter further to enlarge</l>
                        <l>Within a time ſhort,</l>
                        <l>If ye will mark my toyes, and note</l>
                        <l>I will give ye leave to cut my throte</l>
                        <l>If I make not good ſport,</l>
                        <l>Dame Chat I ſay, where be ye, within?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Who have we there maketh ſuch a din?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is a good fellow, maketh no great daunger,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What diccon? Come nere, ye be no ſtraunger,</l>
                        <l>We be faſt ſet at trump man, hard by the fire,</l>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt ſet on the King, if thou come a little nyer.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay, nay, there is no tarying: I muſt be gone again,</l>
                        <l>But firſt for you in councel I have a word or twain.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come hether Dol, Dol, ſit down and play this game,</l>
                        <l>And as thou ſaweſt me do, ſée thou do even the ſame,</l>
                        <l>There is 5. trumps beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quéen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hindmoſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt finde her</l>
                        <l>Take hede of Sim glovers wife, ſhe hath an eye behind her.</l>
                        <l>Now Diccon ſay your will.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay ſoft a little yet,</l>
                        <l>I would not tell my ſiſter, the matter is ſo great,</l>
                        <l>There I will have you ſwear by our dere Lady of Bullaine,</l>
                        <l>S. Dunſtone, and S. Donnyke, with the three Kings of Kul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain,</l>
                        <l>That ye ſhall kéep it ſecret.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs bread that will I doo,</l>
                        <l>As ſecret as mine own thought, by god and the devil two.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Here is gamer gurton your neighbor, a ſad &amp; hevy weight:</l>
                        <l>Her goodly fair red Cock, at home, was ſtole this laſt night.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Gogs ſoul her Cock with the yelow legs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nightly crowed ſo juſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>That cock is ſtollen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>What was he fet out of the hens ruſte?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I can not tell where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> devil he was kept, under key or lock,</l>
                        <l>But Tib hath tikled in Gammers ear, that you ſhould ſteal the cock</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Have I ſtrong hoor? by bread and ſalt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What ſoft, I ſay be ſtill.</l>
                        <l>Say not one word for all this geare.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By the maſs that I will,</l>
                        <l>I wil have the yong hore by the head, and the old trot by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throte</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Not one word dame Chat I ſay, not one word for my cote.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:9"/>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Shal ſuch a begars brawl as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thinkeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> make me a théef</l>
                        <l>The pocks light on her hores ſides, a peſtlence &amp; miſchéefe</l>
                        <l>Come out thou hungry nedy bytche, o that my nails be ſhort.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gogs bred woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hold your peace, this g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re wil els paſs ſport</l>
                        <l>I wold not for an hundred pound, this mater ſhuld be known</l>
                        <l>That I am auctour of this tale, or have abrode it blowen</l>
                        <l>Did ye not ſwear ye wold be ruled, before the tale I told?</l>
                        <l>I ſaid ye muſt all ſecret kéep, and the ſaid ſure ye wolde.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Wold you ſuffer your ſelf diccon, ſuch a ſort, to revile you</l>
                        <l>With ſlaunderous words to blot your name, &amp; ſo to defile you?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No good wife chat I wold be loth ſuch drabs ſhuld blot my name</l>
                        <l>But yet ye muſt ſo order all, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Diccon bare no blame.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Go to then, what is your rede ſay on your minde, ye ſhall me rule herein.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Godamercy to dame chat, in faith thou muſt the gere begin</l>
                        <l>It is twenty pound to a gooſe turd, my gammar wil not tary</l>
                        <l>But hether ward ſhe comes as faſt as her legs can her cary,</l>
                        <l>To brawle with you about her cock, for wel I hard Tib ſay,</l>
                        <l>The cock was roſted in your houſe, to breafaſt yeſterday,</l>
                        <l>And when he had the carcas eaten, the fethers ye our flunge</l>
                        <l>And doll your maid the legs ſhe hid a foot depe in the dunge,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh gracious god my heart is burſtes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Well rule your ſelf a ſpace</l>
                        <l>And gammar gurton when ſhe cometh anon into this place</l>
                        <l>Then to the Quean lets ſée tell her your minde &amp; ſpare not</l>
                        <l>So ſhall Diccon blameleſs bée, and then go to I care not.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then hoor beware her throte, I can a bide no longer</l>
                        <l>In faith old witch it ſhalbe ſéen, which of us two be ſtronger</l>
                        <l>And Diccon but at your requeſt, I wold not ſtay one hour,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Well kéep it in till ſhe be here, and then out let it pour,</l>
                        <l>In the mean while get you in, and make no words of this</l>
                        <l>More of this matter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this hour to here you ſhall not miſs</l>
                        <l>Becauſe I know you are my friend, hide it I cold not doubtleſs</l>
                        <l>Ye know your harm, ſée ye be wiſe about your own buſineſs</l>
                        <l>So fare ye will.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay ſoft Diccon and drink, what Doll I ſay.</l>
                        <l>Bring here a cup of the beſt ale, lets ſée, come quickly away.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:9"/>Hodg. Diccon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>YE ſee maſters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one end tapt of this my ſhort deviſe</l>
                        <l>Now muſt we broche thoter to, before the ſmoke lariſe</l>
                        <l>And by the time they have a while run, I truſt ye need not crave it,</l>
                        <l>But loke what lieth in both their harts ye ar like ſure to have it</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea gogs ſoul, art alive yet? what Diccon dare ich come?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A man is wel hied to truſt to thee, I wil ſay nothing but mum</l>
                        <l>But and ye come any nearer I pray you ſee all be ſweet.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Tuſh man, is gammers neele found, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chould gladly weete,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>She may tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke the it is not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, for if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> had kept thy ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding</l>
                        <l>The devil he wold have fet it out, ev'n hodg at thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod</speaker>
                     <p>Gogs ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, &amp; cold he tel nothing wher y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neele might be found</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ye foliſh dolt, ye were to ſeek, ere we had got our ground,</l>
                        <l>Therfore his tale ſo doubtful was, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I cold not perceive it.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then ich ſe welſomthing was ſaid, chop one day yet to have it</l>
                        <l>But diccon, diccon, did not the devil cry, ho, ho, ho,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hadſt taried where thou ſtoodſt, thou woldeſt have ſaid ſo,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Durſt ſwere of a boke, chard him rore, ſtreight after ich was gon</l>
                        <l>But tel me diccon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knave, let me here it anon.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The horſon talked to me, I know not well of what.</l>
                        <l>One while his tonge it ran, and paltered of a Cat,</l>
                        <l>Another while he ſtamered ſtill upon a Kat,</l>
                        <l>Laſt of all there was nothing but every word Chat, Chat,</l>
                        <l>But this I well perceived before I wolde him rid,</l>
                        <l>Betweene Chat and the Kat, and the Cat the nedle is hid,</l>
                        <l>Now wether Gib our cat have eat it in her mawe,</l>
                        <l>Or Doctor Kat our curat have found it in the ſtraw,</l>
                        <l>Or this same chat your neighbor have ſtollen it, god he knoweth,</l>
                        <l>But by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morow at this time, we ſhall learn how the matter goeth</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Canſt learn to night man, ſeeſt not what is here,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Pointing behinde to his torn breeches.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis not poſſible to make it ſooner appere,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Alas Diccon then chaue no ſhift, but leaſt ich tary to long</l>
                        <l>Hie me to Sim glovers ſhop, there to ſeek for a Thonge,</l>
                        <l>There with this breech to tatche and tye as ich may.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tomorow hodg if we chaunce to meet, ſhall ſee what I will ſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:49842:10"/>
               <head>The ii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>The iii. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Diccon Gammer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>NOw this gere muſt forward go, for here my gammer cometh,</l>
                        <l>Be ſtill a while and ſay nothing, make here a litle rometh.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Good lord, ſhall never be my luck my néele again to ſpie?</l>
                        <l>Alas the while tys paſt my help, where tis ſtill it muſt lie.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now Ieſus gammer gurto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> driveth you to this ſadnes:</l>
                        <l>I fear me by my conſcience, you will ſure fall to madneſs.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Who is that? what Diccon? cham loſt man: fye, fye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Mary fye on them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be worthy, but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld be your troble?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Alas the more ich think on it, my ſorrow it waxeth doble.</l>
                        <l>My goodly toſſing ſporiars néele, chave loſt ich wot not where,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Your néele, whan?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My néele (alas) ich might full ill it ſpare,</l>
                        <l>As god himſelf he knoweth nere one beſide chave.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>If this be all good gammer, I warrant you all is ſave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Why know you any tidings which way my néele is gone?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea that I do doubtleſs, as ye ſhall here anone,</l>
                        <l>A ſée a thing this matter toucheth, within theſe 20 hours,</l>
                        <l>Even at this gate, before my face by a neighbour of yours,</l>
                        <l>She ſtooped me down, and up ſhe toke a nedle or a pin,</l>
                        <l>I durſt be ſworn it was even yours, by all my mothers kin.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It was my néele diccon ich wot, for here even by this poſt</l>
                        <l>Ich ſat, what time as ich up ſtart, and ſo my néele it loſt:</l>
                        <l>Who was it leive ſon? ſpeke ich pray the, &amp; quickly tel me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſuttle quean as any in the town, your neighbour here dame Chat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Dame chat dicco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let me be gone, chil thither in poſt haſte.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Take my councel yet or ye go, for fear ye walk in waſt,</l>
                        <l>It is a murrion crafty drab, and froward to be pleaſed.</l>
                        <l>And ye take not the better way, our nedle yet ye loſe it?</l>
                        <l>For when ſhe took it up, even here before your doores?</l>
                        <l>What ſoft dame chat, (quoth I) that ſame is none of yours</l>
                        <l>Avant (quoth ſhe) ſir knave, what prateſt thou of that I find:</l>
                        <l>I wold y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hadſt kiſt me <hi>I</hi> wot whear: ſhe ment I know behind)</l>
                        <l>And home ſhe went as brag as it had ben a bodelouce.</l>
                        <l>And I after as bold, as it had ben, the goodman of the houſe:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:10"/>But there and ye had hard her, how ſhe began to ſcolde,</l>
                        <l>The tonge it were on patins by him that Judas ſolde,</l>
                        <l>Ech other word I was a knave, and you a hore of hores,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe I ſpake in your behalf, and ſaid the néele was yours.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Gogs bread, and thinks y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> callet thus to kéep my néele me fro?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <l>Let her alone, and ſhe minds non other but eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dreſs you ſo</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By the maſs chil rather ſpend the cots that is on my backe.</l>
                        <l>Thinks the falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uean by ſuch a ſlight that chill my néele lack</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Slep not you gere I counſel you, but of this take good hede</l>
                        <l>Let not be known I told you of it, how well ſoever ye ſpede.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chil in Diccon a cléene aperne to take, and ſet before me,</l>
                        <l>And ich may my néele once ſée, chil ſure remember the.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>The ii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>The v. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Diccon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>HEre will the ſport begin, if theſe two once may méet,</l>
                        <l>Their chere durſt lay money will prove ſcarſly ſwéet</l>
                        <l>My gammer ſure entends to be upon her bones,</l>
                        <l>With ſtaves, or with clubs, or els with coble ſtones.</l>
                        <l>Dame Chat on the other ſide, it ſhe be fare behinde</l>
                        <l>I am right far deceived, ſhe is geven to it of kinde,</l>
                        <l>He that may tarry by it a while, and that but ſhort</l>
                        <l>I warrant him truſt to it, he ſhall ſée all the ſport,</l>
                        <l>Into the town will I, my frendes to vyſit there</l>
                        <l>And hether ſtraight again to ſée thend of this gere</l>
                        <l>In the mean time felowes, pype up your fidles, I ſay take them</l>
                        <l>And let your friendes here ſuch mirth as ye can make them.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>The iii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>The i Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Hodg.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sym glover yet gramercy cham meetley well ſped now,</l>
                        <l>Thart even as good a felow as ever kiſte a cowe,</l>
                        <l>Here is a thing in dede, by the maſs though ich ſpeak it</l>
                        <l>Tom tankards great bald curtal, I think could not breake it</l>
                        <l>And when he ſpyed my neede, to be ſo ſtraight and hard,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:11"/>Hays lent me here his naul, to ſet the giv forward,</l>
                        <l>As for my Gammers néele, the flyenge feind go wéet,</l>
                        <l>Chill not now go to the door <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gain with it to méet:</l>
                        <l>Chould make ſhift good enough and chad a candels end,</l>
                        <l>The chéefe hole in my bréeche, with theſe two chil amend.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>The iii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>The ii Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Gammer. Hodg.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>HOw Hodg, mayſt now be glad, cha news to tell thée</l>
                        <l>Ich know who hais my néele, ich truſt ſoon ſhalt it ſée,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>The devil thou does, haſt hard gammer in deed, or doeſt but jeſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis as true as ſteel Hodg.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Why knoweſt well where didſt leeſe it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Ich know who found it, and took it up, ſhalt ſee or it be long.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gods mother dere, if that be true, farwel both naule an thong</l>
                        <l>But who hais it gammer ſay one chould fain here it diſcloſed.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>That falſe fixen, that ſame dame Chat, that counts her ſelf ſo honeſt</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Who told you ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſame did Diccon the bedlam, which ſaw it done.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Diccon: it is a vengeable knave gammer, tis a bonable horſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                        <l>Can do mo things then that els cham deceyued evil:</l>
                        <l>By the maſs ich ſaw him of late call up a great black devil,</l>
                        <l>O the knave cryed ho, ho, roared and he thundred,</l>
                        <l>And yead bene here, cham ſure yould murrenly ha wondred.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Was not thou afraide Hodg to ſee him in this place?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No, and chad come to me, chould have laid him on the face,</l>
                        <l>Chould have promiſed him.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>But Hodg, had he no horns to puſhe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>As long as your two arms, ſaw ye never Fryer Kuſhe,</l>
                        <l>Painted on a cloth, with a ſide long cowes tayle,</l>
                        <l>And crooked cloven feet, and many a hoked nayle?</l>
                        <l>For al the world (if I ſhuld judg) chould recken him his brother</l>
                        <l>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e even what face Frier ruſh had, the devil had ſuch another</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>New Ieſus mercy hodg, did diccon in him bring?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay gammer (heare me ſpeke) chil tel you a greater thing,</l>
                        <l>The devil (when diccon had him, ich hard him wondrous wéel)</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:11"/>Said plainly (here before us) that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>me that had your neele.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then let us go, and ask her wherfore ſhe minds to keep it,</l>
                        <l>Seing we know ſo much, tware a madneſs now to ſlepe it.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Go to her ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſee ye not where ſhe ſtands in her doors,</l>
                        <l>Bid her geve you the neele, tis none of hers but yours.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>The iii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>The iii. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Gammer. Chat. Hodg.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>DAme Chat cholde pray the fait, let me have that is mine,</l>
                        <l>Chil not this twenty yeres take on fart that is thine</l>
                        <l>Therefore give me mine own and let me live beſide the.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Why art thou crept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> home hether, to mine own doores to chide me:</l>
                        <l>Hence doting drab, auaunt, or I ſhall ſet the further.</l>
                        <l>Intends thou and that knave, mee in my houſe to murther?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tuſh gape not ſo, no woman, ſhalt not yet eat mee,</l>
                        <l>Nor all the frends thou haſt, in this ſhall not intreat mee:</l>
                        <l>Mine own goods I will have, and ask the no beleve,</l>
                        <l>What woman: pore folks muſt have right, though the thing you agreve.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Give thée thy right, and hang the up, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thy baggers broode</l>
                        <l>What wilt thou make me a theefe, and ſay I ſtole thy good?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chil ſay nothing (ich warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thee, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ich ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prove it well</l>
                        <l>Thou fet my good even from my door, cham able this to tell.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Did I (old witch) ſteal oft was thine? how ſhould that thing be known?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Ich can not tel but up thou tokeſt it as though it had bin thine own,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Mary fy on thee, thou old giv, with all my very hart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay fy on thée y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> rampe, thou rig, with al that take thy part.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>A vengeaunce on thoſe lips y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> layeth ſuch things to my charge</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>A vengeance on thoſe callats hips, whoſe conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is ſo large</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Come out Hogge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Come out hog, and let have me right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou argant Witche.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou bawdie bitche, chil make thée curſe this night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>A bag and a wallet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>A carte for a callet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Why weneſt thou thus to prevaile,</l>
                        <l>I hold thee a grote,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:12"/>I ſhall patche thy coat,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou wart as good kiſs my tayl,</l>
                        <l>Thou ſlut, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> kut, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> rakes, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> jakes will not ſhame make the hide</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou skald, thou hald, thou roten, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> glotton, I will no lenger chid the</l>
                        <l>But I will teache the to kéep home.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Wilt thou drunken beaſt?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Stick to her gammer, take her by the head, chil warrant you this feaſt,</l>
                        <l>Smite I ſay gammer,</l>
                        <l>Bite I ſay gammer,</l>
                        <l>I trow ye will bekéene:</l>
                        <l>Where be your nails? claw her by the jawes, pull me out bothe her eyen,</l>
                        <l>Gogs bones gammer, hold up her head?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I trow drab I ſhall dreſſe thée.</l>
                        <l>Tary you knave I hold the a grote, I ſhall make theſe hand bleſs thée</l>
                        <l>Take y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> this old hore for amends, &amp; learn thy tonge wel to tame</l>
                        <l>And ſay thou met at this bickering, not thy fellow but thy dame</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Where is the ſtrong ſtued hore, chil gear a hores mark,</l>
                        <l>Stand out ones way, that ich kill none in the dark:</l>
                        <l>Up gammer and ye be alive, chil feight now for us both,</l>
                        <l>Come no nere me thou ſcalde callet, to kill the ich wer loth.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Art here again thou hoddypeke, what doll bring me out my ſpitte,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chill broche thée with this, him father ſoul, chill conjure that foule ſprete:</l>
                        <l>Let dore ſtand Cock, why coms indeed? kepe dore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> horſon boy.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand to it y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> daſtard for thine ears, iſe teche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a ſluttiſh coy,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Gogs wounds hore, chill make the auaunte, take héed Cock, pull in the latche,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>I faith ſir looſe breche had ye taried ye ſhold have found your match.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Fow ware thy throte loſel, thoeſe pray for all;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Wellſaid gammer by my ſoul,</l>
                        <l>Hoiſe her, ſouſe her, bounce her, trounce her, pull out her throte boule</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Comſt behinde me thou withered witch, &amp; I get once on foot</l>
                        <l>Thouſe pay for all, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> old tarlether, ile teach the what long to it</l>
                        <l>Take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this to make up thy mouth, till time thou come by more</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Up gammer, ſtand on your féete, where is the old hore?</l>
                        <l>Faith would chad her by the face choulde crack her callet crown.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>A hodg, hodg, where was thy help, when fixen had me down?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By the maſs Gammer, but for my ſtaffe, Chat had gone nye to ſpyl you</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:12"/>Ich think the harlot had not cared, and chad not com, to kil you</l>
                        <l>But ſhall we looſe our neele thus,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No Hodg chwarde lothe doo ſoo.</l>
                        <l>Thinkeſt thou chill take that at her hand, no hodg ich tel the no</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Chold yet this fray wer wel take up, &amp; our own néele at home</l>
                        <l>Twill be my chaunce els ſome to kil, where ever it be or whom</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>We have a perſon, (hodg thou knoes) a man eſtemed wiſe</l>
                        <l>Maſt doctor Kat, chil for him ſend, and let me here his adviſe,</l>
                        <l>He will her ſhriue for all this gere, &amp; geve her penaunce ſtrait</l>
                        <l>Weſe have our néele, els dame chat comes nere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gate</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ye mary gammer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ich think beſt: will you now for him ſend</l>
                        <l>The ſooner Doctor Kat be here, the ſooner weſe ha an end,</l>
                        <l>And here gammer Diccons devil, (as iche remember well)</l>
                        <l>Of Cat and Chat, and Doctor Kat, a felloneus tale did tell,</l>
                        <l>Chold you forty pound, that is the way your néele to get again.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Chil ha him ſtrait, call out the boy, weſe make him take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pain</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>What coke I ſay, come out, what devil canſt not here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>How now hodg, how does? gammer, is yet the wether cleare?</l>
                        <l>What wold chaue me to doo</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come hether Cock anon:</l>
                        <l>Hence ſwithe to Doctor Kat, hye the that thou were gone,</l>
                        <l>And pray him come ſpeke with me; cham not well at eaſe,</l>
                        <l>Shait have him at his chamber of els at mother Bees,</l>
                        <l>Els ſéek him at Hobfilchers ſhop, for as charde it reported</l>
                        <l>Thers is the beſt ale in al the town, &amp; now is moſt reſorted.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſhall ich bring him with me Gammer?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea, by and by good Cock.</l>
                        <l>Shalt ſee that ſhalbe here anone, els let me have one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dock</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now gammer ſhall we two go in, and tary for his comming</l>
                        <l>what devil woman pluck up your hart, &amp; leve of al this gloming</l>
                        <l>Though ſhe were ſtronger at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, as ich think ye did find her</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet there ye dreſt the dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſow, what time ye can behind her</l>
                        <l>Nay, nay, cham ſure ſhe loſt not all, for ſet them to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begining</l>
                        <l>And ich doubt not, but ſhe wil make ſmal hoſt of her winning.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>The iii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>The iiii. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Tib. Hodg. Gammer. Cock.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:13"/>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SE gammer, gammer, gib our cat, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afraid what ſhe ayleth</l>
                        <l>She ſtandes me gaſping behinde the door, as though her winde her faileth:</l>
                        <l>Now let ich doubt what gib ſhuld mean, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now ſhe doth ſo dote,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hold hether, ichould twenty pound, your néele is in her throte,</l>
                        <l>Grope her ich ſay, me thinks ich féele it, does not prick your hand?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Ich can féele nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No, ich know thars not within this land,</l>
                        <l>A muriner Cat then Gib is, betwixt the tems and Line,</l>
                        <l>Shaſe as much wit in her head almoſt as chaue in mine,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Faith ſhaſe eaten ſome thing, that will not eaſely down</l>
                        <l>Whether ſhe gar it at home, or abrode in the town</l>
                        <l>Iche cannot tell.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Alas ich fear it be ſome croked pin,</l>
                        <l>And then farewel gib, ſhe is undone, and loſt all ſave the skin,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tib, your néele woman, I ſay: gogs ſoul geve me a knife</l>
                        <l>And chil have it out of her mawe, or els chal loſe my life</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <l>What nay hogd, fy kill not our cat, tis al the cats we ha now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By the maſs dame Chat hays me ſo moved, iche care not what I kill, ma god a vowe:</l>
                        <l>Go to then Lib to this geare, hold up her tayle and take her,</l>
                        <l>Chilſe what debit is in her guts, chil take y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> paines to rake her,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Rake a Cat Hodg, what woldſt thou do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What thinckſt that cham not able?</l>
                        <l>Did not Tom Tankard rake his Curtal toore day ſtanding in the ſtable?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Soft be content, lets here what news Cock bringeth from maiſt Rat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gammer chave ben ther as you had, you wot wel about what</l>
                        <l>I will not be long before he come, ich durſt ſwear of a book</l>
                        <l>He bids you ſée ye be at home, and there fore him to look.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Where didſt thou finde him bay, was he not wher I told thée?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yes, yes even at Hobfilchers houſe, by him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bought and ſold me</l>
                        <l>A cup of Ale had in his hand, and a crab lay in the fier,</l>
                        <l>Chad much a do to go and come, all was ſo full of mier:</l>
                        <l>And Gammer one thing I can tell, Hobfilchers naule was loſte</l>
                        <l>And Doctor Rat found it again, hard beſtde the door poſte,</l>
                        <l>I choulde penny can ſay ſomething, your néele again to fet.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cham glad to hear ſo much Cock, than truſt he will not let</l>
                        <l>To help us herein beſt he can, therefore till time he come</l>
                        <l>Let us go in, if there be ought to get thou ſhall have ſome.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:49842:13"/>
               <head>The ii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>The iiii. Sceam.</head>
                  <stage>Doctor Rat. Gammer Gurton.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Man were better twenty times, be a bandog &amp; barke,</l>
                        <l>Then here among ſuch a ſort, be pariſh prieſt or clarke</l>
                        <l>Where he ſhall never be at reſt one piſſing while a day.</l>
                        <l>But he muſt trudge about the towne, this way, and that way,</l>
                        <l>Here to a drab, there to a theefe, his ſhoes to teare and rent</l>
                        <l>And that which is worſt of all, at every knaves commaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
                        <l>I had not ſit the ſpace to drinke two pots of ale,</l>
                        <l>But Gammer gurtons ſory boy, was ſtraite way at my taile.</l>
                        <l>And ſhe was ſicke, and I muſt come, to do I wot not what,</l>
                        <l>If once her ſingers end but ake, trudge, call for Doctor Rat,</l>
                        <l>And when I come not at their call, I only thereby looſe,</l>
                        <l>For I am ſure to lacke therefore a tythe pyg or a gooſe:</l>
                        <l>I warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you when truth is known, &amp; told they have their tale</l>
                        <l>The matter where about I come, (is not worth a half peny worth of ale,</l>
                        <l>Yet muſt I talke ſo ſage and ſmothe, as though I were a gloſſer</l>
                        <l>Els or the yer come at an end, I ſhalbe ſure the loſer,</l>
                        <l>What worke ye ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer gurto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? how here is your friend M. Rat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>G.</speaker>
                     <p>A good M. Doctor, cha troubled, cha troubled you, chwot wel that</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>How do ye woman, be ye luſtie, or be ye not wel at eaſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By gys maſter cham not ſich, but yet chaue a diſeaſe.</l>
                        <l>Chad a foule turne now of late, chill tell it you by gigs.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>Hach your browne cow caſt hir calfe, or your ſandy ſowe her pigs</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>No but chad ben as good they had, as this ich wot weel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                     <p>What is the matter,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Alas, alas, cha loſt my good néele,</l>
                        <l>My neele I ſay, and wot ye what: a drab came by and ſpied it</l>
                        <l>And when I aſked hir for the ſame, the filth flatly denied it.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>What was ſhe that:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A dame ich warrant you: we began to ſcold and brawle</l>
                        <l>Alas, alas, come hether Hodge? this wretche can tell you all.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>The iiii. Acte.</head>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>The ii. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>Hodge. Doctor Rat. Gammer. Diccon. Chat.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>GOd morow gaffer Vicar.</l>
                        <l>Come on fellow let us heare.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:14"/>Thy dame hath ſaid to me, thou knoweſt of all this geare,</l>
                        <l>Lets ſée what thou canſt ſay?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Bym ſay ſir that ye ſhall,</l>
                        <l>What matter ſo ever here was done, ich can tell your maſhip</l>
                        <l>My Gammer gurton hear ſée now,</l>
                        <l>Cat her down at this door ſée now,</l>
                        <l>And as ſhe began to ſtir her, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>her néele fell in the floore, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>And while her ſtaff ſhe took, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>at gib her Cat to fling, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>Her néele was loſt in the floor, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>is not this a wondrous thing, ſée now?</l>
                        <l>Then came the quean Dame Chat, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>to ask for hir black cup, ſée now:</l>
                        <l>And even here at this gate, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>ſhe took that néele up, ſée now:</l>
                        <l>My Gammer then ſhe yeede, ſée now,</l>
                        <l>hir néele again to bring, ſee now,</l>
                        <l>And was caught by the head, ſee now,</l>
                        <l>is not this a wondrous thing, ſee now?</l>
                        <l>She tare my Gammers cote, ſee now</l>
                        <l>and ſcratched hir by the face, ſee now</l>
                        <l>Chad thought ſhad ſtopt hir throte, ſee now</l>
                        <l>is not this a wondrous caſe, ſee now?</l>
                        <l>When ich ſaw this, ich was wroth, ſee now</l>
                        <l>and ſtart between them twain, ſee now</l>
                        <l>Els ich durſt take a book othe, ſee now</l>
                        <l>my gammer had been ſlain, ſee now.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This is even the whole matter, as Hodg has plainly told</l>
                        <l>And chould fain be quiet for my part, that chould.</l>
                        <l>But help us good maſter, beſeech ye that ye doo</l>
                        <l>Els ſhall we both be beaten and loſe our neele too</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What wold ye have me to doo? tell me that I were gone</l>
                        <l>I do the beſt that I can, to ſet you both at one.</l>
                        <l>But be ye ſure dame Chat hath this your neele found?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Here comes the man that ſee hir take it up off the ground,</l>
                        <l>Ask him your ſelf maſter Rat if ye beleve not me</l>
                        <l>And help me to my neele, for gods ſake and ſaint charitie.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come nere diccon, and let us hear, what thou can expreſs.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:14"/>Wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be ſworne ſeeſt dame chat, this womans neele have?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay by S. Benit will I not, then might ye think me raue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>G.</speaker>
                     <l>Why didſt not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> tell me ſo even here canſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> for ſhame deny it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <l>I mary gammer: but I ſaid I wold not abide by it,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <l>Will you ſay a thing, and ſticke to it to trie it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Stick to it quoth you maſter rat, mary ſir I defy it,</l>
                        <l>Nay there is many an honeſt man, when he ſuche blaſtes hath blowne,</l>
                        <l>In his freindes ears, he woulde be loth the ſame by him were knowne:</l>
                        <l>If ſuch a toy be uſed oft among the honeſtie,</l>
                        <l>It may be ſeme a ſimple man, of your and my degree.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <l>Then we be never the nearer, for all that you can tell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yes mary ſir, if ye will do by mine adviſe and counſaile,</l>
                        <l>If mother chat ſe al us here, ſhe knoweth how the matter goes</l>
                        <l>Therefore I red you three, go hence, and within keep cloſe;</l>
                        <l>And I will into dame chats houſe, and ſo the matter uſe,</l>
                        <l>That or you cold go twiſe to church, I warant you here news:</l>
                        <l>She ſhall looke well about her, but I durſt lay a pledge,</l>
                        <l>Ye ſhall of gammers neele, have ſhortly better knowledg.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <l>Now gentle Diccon do ſo, and good ſir let us trudge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <l>By the maſſe I may not tarry ſo long to be your judge,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tys but a little while man, what take ſo much paine;</l>
                        <l>If I here none wes of it, I will come ſooner againe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                     <l>Tary ſo much, good maſter Doctor of your gentlenes,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <l>Then let us hie inward, and Diccon ſpeede thy buſines.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now ſirs do you no more, but kepe my counſaile juſt,</l>
                        <l>And Doctor Rat ſhall thus catch ſome good I truſt,</l>
                        <l>But mother Chat my goſſap, talke firſt with all I muſt:</l>
                        <l>For ſhe muſt be chief captaine to lay the Rat in the duſt.</l>
                        <l>God deven dame Chat in faith, and well met in this place.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <l>God deven my friend Diccon, whether walke ye this pace:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By my truth even to you, to learne how the world goeth,</l>
                        <l>Hard ye no more of the other matter, ſay me now by your troth?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O yes diccon: here the olde hoore, &amp; hodge that great knave.</l>
                        <l>But in faith I would thou hadſt ſene, o lord I dreſt them brave,</l>
                        <l>She bar me two or three ſouſes behind in the nape of the necke</l>
                        <l>Till I made hir olde weſen, to anſwer again kecke:</l>
                        <l>And Hodge that dirty daſtard, that at hir elbow ſtandes,</l>
                        <l>If one paire of legs had not bene worth two paire of hands</l>
                        <l>He had had his bearde ſhaven, if my nayles wold have ſerved</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:15"/>And not without a cauſe, for the knave it well deſerved.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>By the maſſe I can the thank wench, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> didſt ſo wel acquite' the</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And thadſt ſeene him Diccon, it wold have made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſhite the</l>
                        <l>For laughter, the horſen dolt at laſt caught up a club,</l>
                        <l>As though he would have ſlaine the maſter devil Belſabub,</l>
                        <l>But I ſet him ſoone inwarde.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O Lord there is the thing,</l>
                        <l>That Hodge is ſo offended, that makes him ſtarte and flyng.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Why? makes the knave any moyling, as ye have ſeene or hard</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Even now I ſawe him laſt, like a mad man he farde,</l>
                        <l>And ſware vp heaven and hell, he would a wreake his ſorrow</l>
                        <l>And leve you never a hen a live by viii. of the clock tomorow,</l>
                        <l>Therefore mark what I ſay, and my wordes ſee that ye truſt</l>
                        <l>Your hens be as good as dead, if ye leave them on the ruſte.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                     <p>The knave dare as well go hang himſelf, as go upon my grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Wel yet take hede I ſay, I muſt tel you my tale round,</l>
                        <l>Have you not about your houſe, behind your furnace or leade,</l>
                        <l>A hole where a crafty knave may creepe in for neade?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes by the maſſe, a hole broke down, even w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in theſe ii. dayes,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Hodge, he intends this ſame night, to ſlip in there awayes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>O Chriſt that I were ſure of it, in faith he ſhuld have his mede</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Watch wel, for the knave wil be there as ſure as is your crede</l>
                        <l>I wold ſpend my ſelfe a ſhilling to have him ſwinged well.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I am as glad as a woman can be of this thing to here tell,</l>
                        <l>By gogs bones when he cometh, now that I know the matter</l>
                        <l>He ſhall ſure at the firſt ſkip, to leape in ſcalding water:</l>
                        <l>With a worſe turne beſides, when he will, let him come.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I tell you as my ſiſter, you know what meaneth mum,</l>
                        <l>Now lacke I but my doctor, to play his part againe..</l>
                        <l>And lo where he cometh towards, peradventure to his paine.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>What good newes Diccon? fellow, is mother chat at houſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>She is ſyr, and ſhe is not, but it pleaſe her to whome:</l>
                        <l>Yet did I take her tardy, as ſubtle as ſhe was.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>The thing that thou wentſt for, haſt thou brought it to paſſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I have done that I have done, be it worſe, be it better.</l>
                        <l>And dame Chat at her wyts ende, I have almoſt ſet her,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>Why haſt thou ſpied the naele, quickly I pray thee tell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I have ſpied it in faith ſir, I handled my ſelfe ſo well,</l>
                        <l>And yet the crafty queane had almoſt take my trumpe.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:15"/>But or all came to an ende, I ſet her in a dumpe:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſo I pray thee Diccon?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mary ſir will ye heare?</l>
                        <l>She was clapt downe on the backſide, by cocks mother dere,</l>
                        <l>And there ſhe ſat ſowing a halter, or a bande,</l>
                        <l>With no other thing ſave gammers nedle in her hande,</l>
                        <l>As ſoone as any knocke, if the filth be in doubte,</l>
                        <l>She needes but once puffe, and her candle is out:</l>
                        <l>Now I ſir knowing of every doore the pin.</l>
                        <l>Came nicely, and ſaid no worde, till time I was within,</l>
                        <l>And there ſawe the néele, even with theſe two eyes.</l>
                        <l>Who ever ſay the contrary, I will ſweare he lyes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>O Diccon that I was not there, then in thy ſteade.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Well, if ye will be ordred, and do by my reade.</l>
                        <l>I will bring you to a place, as the houſe ſtandes.</l>
                        <l>Where ye ſhall take the drab, with the néele in her handes,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For Gods ſake do ſo Diccon, and I will gage my gowne,</l>
                        <l>To geve thee a full pot of the beſt ale in the towne,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Follow me but a litle, and marke what I will ſay,</l>
                        <l>Lay downe your gown beſide you, go to, come on your way:</l>
                        <l>Se ye not what is here, a hole wherein ye may creepe</l>
                        <l>Into the houſe, and ſodenly unwares among them leape,</l>
                        <l>There ſhal ye finde the Bichfox, and the néele together,</l>
                        <l>Do as I bid you man, come on your wayes hether.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Art thou ſure diccon the ſwel tub ſtandes not here about?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I was within my ſelfe man even now, there is no doubt,</l>
                        <l>Go ſoftly, make no noiſe, give me your foote ſir Iohn,</l>
                        <l>Here will I waite upon you, till you come out anon.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>Help Diccon, out alas, I ſhall be ſlain among them,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If they give you not the nedle, tel them that ye wil ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them</l>
                        <l>Ware that, how my wenches, have ye caught the Foxe,</l>
                        <l>That uſed to make revel among your hennes and Cocks,</l>
                        <l>Save his life yet for his order, though he ſuſteine ſome paine</l>
                        <l>Gogs bread, I am afraide, they will beate out his braine.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Wo worth the houre that I came heare.</l>
                        <l>And wo worth him that wrought this geare,</l>
                        <l>A ſort of drabs and queans have me bleſt,</l>
                        <l>Was ever creature halfe ſo evil dreſt?</l>
                        <l>Who ever it wrought, and firſt did invent it,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:16"/>He ſhall I warrant him, ere long repent it.</l>
                        <l>I will ſpend I have without my skin,</l>
                        <l>But he ſhall be brought to the plight <hi>I</hi>'um in;</l>
                        <l>Maſter Bayly <hi>I</hi> trow, and he be worth his eares,</l>
                        <l>Will ſnaffle theſe murderers and all that them beares,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I</hi> will ſurely neither byte nore ſuppe</l>
                        <l>Till <hi>I</hi> fetch him hether, this matter to take up.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>The v. Acte.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>The i. Sceane</head>
                  <stage>Maſter Bayly. Doctor Rat.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I Can perceive none other, I ſpeke it from my hart</l>
                        <l>But either ye ar in all the fault, or els in the greateſt part.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If it be counted his fault, beſides all his greeves</l>
                        <l>When a poor man is ſpoyled, and beaten among theeves,</l>
                        <l>Then I confeſſe my fault herein, at this ſeaſon,</l>
                        <l>But I hope you will not urge ſo much againſt reaſon:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And me thinkes by your own tale, of all that ye name,</l>
                        <l>If any plaid the theefe you were the very ſame:</l>
                        <l>The women they did nothing, as your words made probation,</l>
                        <l>But ſtootly withſtood your forciable invaſion,</l>
                        <l>If that a theefe at your window, to enter ſhould begin,</l>
                        <l>Wold you hold forth your hand, and helpe to pull him in?</l>
                        <l>Or you wold kepe him out: I pray you anſwere me.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mary hope him out, and a good cauſe why:</l>
                        <l>But I am no theefe ſir, but an honeſt learned Clarke.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea but who knoweth that, when he meets you in the dark?</l>
                        <l>I am ſure your learning ſhines not out at your noſe,</l>
                        <l>Was it any marvaile, though the poor woman aroſe</l>
                        <l>And ſtrat up, being afraide of that was in hir purſe,</l>
                        <l>Me thinke you may be glad that your lucke was worſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>Is not this evil ynough, I pray you thinke? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Showing his broken head.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea but a man in the darke of chaunces do wincke,</l>
                        <l>As ſoone meets his father as any other man</l>
                        <l>Becauſe for lacke of light, decerne him he ne can,</l>
                        <l>Might it not have bene our lucke, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpit to have bene ſlain?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I thinke I am little better, my ſcalpe is cloven to the brain,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:16"/>If there be all the remedy, I know who beares the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ockes,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By my trath and well worthy, beſides to kiſſe the ſtockes</l>
                        <l>To come in on the backe ſide, when ye might go about,</l>
                        <l>I know non ſuch, unles they long to have their braines knockt out</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Well, will you be ſo good ſir, as talke with dame Chat;</l>
                        <l>And know what ſhe intended, I aske no more but that.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let her be called fellow becauſe of maſter doctor,</l>
                        <l>I warrant in this caſe, ſhe will be hir owne Proctor,</l>
                        <l>She will tell hir owne tale in metter or in proſe,</l>
                        <l>And byd you ſeeke your remedy, and ſo go wype your noſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>The vi. Acte.</head>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>The ii. Sceane.</head>
                  <stage>M. Baily. Chat. D. Rat. Gammer. Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>DAme Chat, maſter doctor upon you here complained</l>
                        <l>That you and your maides ſhuld him much miſorder,</l>
                        <l>And taketh many an oth, that no word he fained,</l>
                        <l>Laying to your charge, how you thought him to murder:</l>
                        <l>And on his part againe, that ſame man ſaith furder,</l>
                        <l>He never offended you in word nor intent,</l>
                        <l>To heare you anſwer hereto, we have now for you ſent.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That I wold have murdered him, fye on him wretch,</l>
                        <l>And evil mought he thee for it, our Lord I beſeech.</l>
                        <l>I will ſwere on all the bookes that opens and ſhuttes</l>
                        <l>He faineth this tale out of his owne guttes,</l>
                        <l>For this ſeven weekes with me, I am ſure he ſat not downe</l>
                        <l>Nay ye have other minions, in the other end of the town,</l>
                        <l>Where ye were liker to catch ſuch a blow,</l>
                        <l>Then any where els, as farre as I know.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Be like then maſter Doctor, your ſtripe there ye got not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Think you <hi>I</hi> am ſo mad, that where <hi>I</hi> was bet <hi>I</hi> wat not?</l>
                        <l>Will ye beleve this queane, before ſhe hath tryd it?</l>
                        <l>It is not the firſt dede ſhe hath done, and afterward denide it.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>What man, will you ſay <hi>I</hi> broke your head?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>How canſt thou prove the contrary?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay how proteſt thou that <hi>I</hi> did the deade?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Too plainly, by S. Mary.</l>
                        <l>This profe <hi>I</hi> trow may ſerve, though <hi>I</hi> no word ſpoke. </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Showing his broken head.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:17"/>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Becauſe thy head is broken, was it I that it broke:</l>
                        <l>I ſaw the Rat I tel thee, not once within this fornight.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No mary, thou ſaweſt me not, for why thou hadſt no light,</l>
                        <l>But I felt thee for all the darke, beſhrew thy ſmothe cheekes,</l>
                        <l>And thou groped me, this wil declare, any day this ſix weekes </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Showing his head.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Anſwere me to this M. Rat, when caught you this harme of yours?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>A while a go ſir, god he knoweth, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in les the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe ii. hours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Dame Chat was there none with you? (confeſſe I faith) about that ſeaſon.</l>
                        <l>What woman, let it be what it wil, tis neither felony nor treaſon</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yes by my faith maſter Baily,, there was a knave not farre</l>
                        <l>Who caught one good Philup on the brow with a dore barre</l>
                        <l>And well was he worthy, as it ſemed to me,</l>
                        <l>But what is that to this man, ſince this was not be?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Who was it then? lets here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Alas ſir, aſk you that?</l>
                        <l>Is it not made plain inough by the own mouth of dame chat?</l>
                        <l>The time agreeth, my head is broken, her tong cannot lie,</l>
                        <l>Onely upon a bare, nay ſhe ſaith it was not I.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No mary was it not indeed, ye ſhal here by this one thing,</l>
                        <l>This after noon a friend of mine for good wil gave we warning</l>
                        <l>And bad me wel loke to my ruſte, and all my Capons pennes,</l>
                        <l>For if I toke not better heed, a knave wold have my hennes,</l>
                        <l>Then I to ſave my goods, toke ſo much pains as him to watch</l>
                        <l>And as good fortune ſerved me, it was my chance him for to catch</l>
                        <l>What ſtrooks he bare away, or other what was his gains</l>
                        <l>I wot not, but ſure I am, he had ſomething for his pains.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet telles thou not who it was.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Who it was? a falſe theefe,</l>
                        <l>That came like a falſe Foxe, my pullain to kil and miſcheefe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>But knoweſt thou not his name?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I know it, but what than?</l>
                        <l>It was that crafty cull yon Hodge my gammer gurtons man.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cal me the knave hether, he ſhall ſure kiſſe the ſtockes.</l>
                        <l>I ſhall teach him a leſſon for filching hens or cocks.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I marvail maſter Baily, ſo bleared be your eyes.</l>
                        <l>An egge is not ſo full of meat, as ſhe is full of lies:</l>
                        <l>When ſhe hath plaid this pranke, to excuſe all this geare,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:17"/>She layeth the fault in ſuch a one, as I know was not there.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Was he yot there? loke on his pate, that ſhalbe his witnes,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>I wold my head were halfe ſo hole, I wold ſeek no redreſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>God bleſſe you gammer Gurton.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>God dilde you maſter mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou haſt a knave w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in thy houſe, hodge, a ſervant of thine.</l>
                        <l>They tell me that buſte knave, is ſuch a filching one,</l>
                        <l>That Hen, Pig, Gooſe, or Capon, thy neighbour can have none</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By god cham much ameved, to hear anie ſuch report:</l>
                        <l>Hodge was not wont ich trow, to have him in that ſort.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A theeviſher knave is not on live, more filching, nor more falſe,</l>
                        <l>Manie a truer man then he has hanged up by the halſe.</l>
                        <l>And thou his dame of all his theft, thou art the ſole receaver,</l>
                        <l>For hodge to catch, and thou to keep, I never knew none better</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sir reverence of your maſterdome, and you were out of doore,</l>
                        <l>Chold be ſo bold for all hir brags, to call hir arrant whore.</l>
                        <l>And ich knew Hodge ſo bad as tow, ich wiſh me endleſſe ſorrow</l>
                        <l>And chould not take the pains, to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him up before to morow.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>What have I ſtoln from the or thine thou ilfavored old trot?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A great deal more (by God bleſt) then chever by the got,</l>
                        <l>That thou knoweſt well I need not ſay it.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Stoppe there I ſay,</l>
                        <l>And tell me here I pray you, this matter by the waie:</l>
                        <l>How chaunce hodge is not here? him wold I fain have had.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas Sir, heel be here anon, ha be handled too bad,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Maſter Baily, ſir ye be not ſuch a fool well I know,</l>
                        <l>But ye perceive by this lingring, there is a pad in the ſtraw.</l>
                        <l>Thinking that Hodge, his head was broke, and that gammer</l>
                        <l>Wold not let him come before them.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Chil ſhew you his face ich warrant the, lo-now where he is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come on fellow, it is told me thou art a ſhrew iwyſſe.</l>
                        <l>Thy neighbours hens y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> takeſt, and plaies the two legged fore</l>
                        <l>Their chikens, &amp; their capons too, &amp; now and then their Cocks</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Ich defy them all that dare it ſay, chame as true as the beſt,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Wart not-y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> take within this hour in dame chats hens neſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Take there, no maſter chould not dot for a houſe ful of gold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art the devil in thy cote, ſwarthis I dare be bold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Swear me no ſwearing quean, the devil he geve the ſorrow,</l>
                        <l>As is not worth a gnat, thou canſt ſwear till to morrow.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:18"/>Where is the harme he hath? ſhew it by gods bread,</l>
                        <l>Ye beat him with a witnes, but the ſtripes light on my head.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Bet me, gogs bleſſed bodie, chold firſt ich trow have burſt the,</l>
                        <l>Ich think and chad my hands looſe callet chould have cruſt the.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou ſhirte knave I trow y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> full weight of my fiſt</l>
                        <l>I am fowlie deceived, unles thy head and my door bar kiſte.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold thy chat whore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> crieſt ſo loud, can no man els be hard?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Well knave, &amp; I had the alone, I wold ſurelie rap thy coſtard.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir anſwer me to this, is thy head whole or broken?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea maſter Baily, bleſt be everie good token.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Is my head whole? ich warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you, tis neither ſcurby nor ſcald,</l>
                        <l>What you foul beaſt, does think tis either pild or bald?</l>
                        <l>Nay ich thank god, chil not for all that thou maiſt ſpend,</l>
                        <l>That chad one ſcab on my narſe, as brode as thy ſingers end.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Come nearer here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes that ich dare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By our Lady here is no harme,</l>
                        <l>Hodges head is hole enough, for all dame Chats charme:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By gogs bleſt, how ever the thing he clockes or ſmolders,</l>
                        <l>I know the blows he bare awaie, either w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> head or ſhoulders,</l>
                        <l>Cameſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not knave within this hour, creeping into my pens,</l>
                        <l>And there was caught within my houſe, groping among my hens?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A plage both on thy hens &amp; thee, a cart whore, a cart,</l>
                        <l>Chould I were ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged as hie as a tree, &amp; chware as falſe as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art</l>
                        <l>Geve my gammer again her waſhical y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſtole away in thy lap.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea maſter Baily there is a thing, you know not on may hap</l>
                        <l>This drab ſhe kepes away my good, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> devil he might her ſnare</l>
                        <l>Ich pray you that ich might have a right action on her.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Have I thy good old filth, or any ſuch old ſowes?</l>
                        <l>I am as true, I wold thou knew, as ſkin between thy browes,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Many a truer hath been hang'd, though you eſcape the danger</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt anſwer by gods pitie for this thy foul ſlaunder.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye charge hir withal? to ſay ſo, ye do not wel,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Mary a vengeance to hir hart, the whore has ſtoln my néele.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy nedle old witch, how ſo? it were alms thy ſcul to knock,</l>
                        <l>So didſt thou ſay, the other day, that I had ſtoln thy Cock,</l>
                        <l>And roſted him to my breaſtfaſt, which ſhall not be forgotten;</l>
                        <l>The devil pul out thy lying tong, and teeth that be rotten.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Geve me my néele, as for my cocke, chould be verie loth</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:18"/>That chuld here tell be ſhuld hang on thy falſe faith and troth.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Your taſke is ſuch, I can ſcarſe learn who ſhuld be moſt in fault</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet ſhall ye find no other wight, ſave ſhe, by bred &amp; ſalt</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baity.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Kepe ye content a while; ſe that your tonges ye hold,</l>
                        <l>Me thinks you ſhuld remember, this is no place to ſcolde,</l>
                        <l>How knoweſt thou gammer gurton, dame Chat, thy nedle had?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>To name you ſir the partie; chould not be verie glad</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea but we muſt needs hear it, and therefore ſaie it boldlie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Such one as told the tale, full ſoberlie and coldlie,</l>
                        <l>Even he that loked on, will ſwear on a booke,</l>
                        <l>What time this drunken goſſip, my fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> long néele up tooke,</l>
                        <l>Diccon (maſter) the Bedlam, cham ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> ſure ye know him.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A falſe knave by Gods pitie, ye were but a fool to trow him,</l>
                        <l>I durſt aventure well the price of my beſt cap,</l>
                        <l>That when the end is known, all will turn to a jape.</l>
                        <l>Told he not you that beſides, ſhe ſtole your Cocke that tide?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No maſter, no indeed, for then he ſhuld have lied,</l>
                        <l>My cocke is I thanke Chriſt, ſafe and well a fine.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea but that ragged colt, that whore that tib of thine</l>
                        <l>Said plainlie thy cocke was ſtolne, and in my houſe was eaten,</l>
                        <l>That lying cut is loſt, that ſhe is not ſwinged and beaten,</l>
                        <l>And yet for all my good name, it were a ſmall amends;</l>
                        <l>I picke not this geare (hearſt thou) out of my fingers ends.</l>
                        <l>But he that hard it told me, who thou of late didſt name,</l>
                        <l>Diccon whom all men knows, it was the verie ſame:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This is the caſe, you loſt your nedle about the dores,</l>
                        <l>And ſhe anſwers again, ſhe haſe no cocke of yours;</l>
                        <l>Thus in your talke and Action, from that you do intend,</l>
                        <l>She is whole five mile wide, from that ſhe doth defend:</l>
                        <l>Will you ſay ſhe hath your Cocke?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>No mery ſir that chil not,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you confeſſe hir neele?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Will I? no ſir will I not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Then there lieth all the matter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Soft maſter by the way,</l>
                        <l>Ye know ſhe could do little, and ſhe could not ſay naie.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea but he that made one lie about your cocke ſtealing,</l>
                        <l>Will not ſticke to make another, what time lies be in dealing.</l>
                        <l>I wéene the end will prove this brawle did firſt ariſe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:19"/>Vpon no other ground, but onely Diccons lies.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though ſome be lies as you belike have eſpied them</l>
                        <l>Yet other ſome be true, by proofe I have wel tried them</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>What other thing beſide this dame Chat?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mary ſir even this,</l>
                        <l>The tale I tulde before, the ſelfe ſame tale it was his,</l>
                        <l>He gave me like a frende warning againſt my loſſe,</l>
                        <l>Els had my hens been ſtoln, eche one, by Gods croſſe.</l>
                        <l>He tolde me Hodge wold come, and in he came indeed,</l>
                        <l>But as the matter chaunſed, with greater haſt then ſpeed.</l>
                        <l>This truth was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>id, and true was found, as trulie <hi>I</hi> report.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>If Doctor Rat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e not deceived, it was o' another ſort.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By Gods mother thou and he, be a cople of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tle foxes,</l>
                        <l>Between you and Hodge, I bear awaie the boxes.</l>
                        <l>Did not dicco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apoint the place, wher y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhuldſt ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to meet him?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes by the maſſe, &amp; if he came, bad me not ſticke to ſpeet hym.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gods ſacrament the villain knave hath dreſt us round about,</l>
                        <l>He is the cauſe of all this brawl, that dirty ſhitten loute:</l>
                        <l>When gammer gurton here complained, &amp; made a ruful mone,</l>
                        <l>I heard him ſwear y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you had gotten hir nedle that was gone.</l>
                        <l>And this to try he furder ſaid, he was full loth how be it,</l>
                        <l>He was content ſmall ado, to bring me where to ſee it.</l>
                        <l>And where ye ſat, he ſaith full certian, if I wold folow his read,</l>
                        <l>Into your houſe a privie waie, he wold me guid and lead.</l>
                        <l>And where ye had it in your hands, ſewing about a clowt,</l>
                        <l>And ſet me in the backe hole, therebie to finde you out:</l>
                        <l>And whiles I ſought a quietnes, creeping upon my knees,</l>
                        <l>I found the weight of your door bar, for my reward and fees.</l>
                        <l>Such is the lucke that ſome men gets, while they begin to mel,</l>
                        <l>In ſetting at one ſuch as were out; minding to make all well:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hogd.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Was not well bleſt ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer, to ſcape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcour &amp; chad ben there,</l>
                        <l>Then chad ben dreſt be like, as ill by the maſſe, as gaffer vicar.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mary ſir, here is a ſport alone, I loked for ſuch an end,</l>
                        <l>If diccon had not plaied the knave, this had ben ſone amend.</l>
                        <l>My gammer here he made a fool, and dreſt hir as ſhe was,</l>
                        <l>And goodwife Chat he ſet to ſcodl, till both parteis, cried alas.</l>
                        <l>And D. Rat was not behind, whiles Chat his crown did pare,</l>
                        <l>I wold the knave had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtarke blind, if hodge had not his ſhare.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cham meetlie wel ſped alredie amongs, cham dreſt like a coult</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:19"/>And chad not had the better wit, chad been made a doult.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir knave make haſt dicco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were here, fetch him where ever he be,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <p>Fie on the villian, fie, fie, that makes us thus agree.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Fie on him knave, with all my hart, now fie, and fie again,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>Now fie on him may I beſt ſaie, whom he hath almoſt ſlain</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lo where he commeth at kand, belike he was not fare,</l>
                        <l>Diccon here be two or three, thy companie cannot ſpare.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>God bleſſs you, and you maie be bleſt ſo manie all at once,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come knave, it were a good deed to gled the by cockes bones.</l>
                        <l>Seeſt not thy handiwarke, ſir Rat can you forhear him?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance on thoſe hands life, for my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds cam not neer him</l>
                        <l>The horſen prieſt hath lift the pot in ſome of theſe alewives chaires.</l>
                        <l>That his head wold not ſerve him belike, to come down the ſtaires.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bai.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay ſoft, thou maiſt not plaie the knave, &amp; have this language to</l>
                        <l>If thou thy tong bridle a while; the better maiſt thou do.</l>
                        <l>Confeſſe the truth as <hi>I</hi> ſhall ask, and ceaſe a while to fable,</l>
                        <l>And for thy fault I promiſe the, thy handling ſhalbe reaſonable.</l>
                        <l>Haſt thou not made a lie or two, to ſet theſe two by the ears?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What if I have? five hundred ſuch have I ſeen within theſe ſeven years:</l>
                        <l>I am ſory for nothing elſe but that I ſee not the ſport,</l>
                        <l>Which was between them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they met, as they themſelves report.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bay.</speaker>
                     <p>The greateſt thing maſter rat, ye ſe how he is dreſt,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>What devil need he be groping ſo deep, in goodwife Chat he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s neſt</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea but it was thy drift to bring him into the briars</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gods bread, hath not ſuch an old fool wit to ſave his ears?</l>
                        <l>He ſhoweth himſelf herein you ſee, ſo verie coxe,</l>
                        <l>The Cat was not-ſo madly alured by the Foxe,</l>
                        <l>To run into the ſnares, was ſet for him doubtleſſe,</l>
                        <l>For he leapt in for mice, and this ſir John for madneſs.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Well and ye ſhift no better, ye loſel, lither, and laſie,</l>
                        <l>I will go near for this, to make ye leape at a Daſie.</l>
                        <l>In the kings name maſter Baily, I charge you ſet him faſt,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>What faſt at cards or on ſleep? it is the thing I did laſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat</speaker>
                     <p>Nay faſt in fetter falſe varlet, according to thy deeds</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Maſter doctor there is no remedy, I muſt intreat you needs</l>
                        <l>Some other kinde of puniſhment,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nay by all Halows</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:20"/>His puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t if I may judge, ſhalbe naught tis but the gallous</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>That were too ſore, a ſpiritual man to be ſo extream.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>Is he worthy any better, ſir how do you judge and deam?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>I graunt him worthy puniſhment, but by no wiſe ſo great.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It is a ſhame ich tell you plain, for ſuch falſe knaves intreat</l>
                        <l>He has almoſt undone us all, that is as true as ſteel:</l>
                        <l>And yet for all this great add, cham never the nere my néele.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Canſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not ſay any thing to that diccon, with leaſt or moſt:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea mary ſir, thus much I can ſay well, the néele is loſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay canſt not thou tell which way that nedle may be found?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>No by my fay ſir, though I might have an hundred pound.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou lier lickdiſh, didſt not ſay the néele wold be gitton?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No hodge, by the ſame token you were at that time beſhitten,</l>
                        <l>For fear of Hobgobling, you wot well what I mean;</l>
                        <l>As long as it is ſence, I fear me yet ye be ſcarce clean.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Well maſter rat, you muſt both learn, &amp; teach us to forgeve,</l>
                        <l>Since Diccon hath confeſſion ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and is ſo clean ſhreve,</l>
                        <l>If ye to me conſent, to amend this heavie chaunce,</l>
                        <l>I will injoyn him here ſome open kind of penaunce:</l>
                        <l>Of this condition, where ye know my fee is twenty pence,</l>
                        <l>For the bloodſhed, I am agreed with you here to diſpence;</l>
                        <l>Ye ſhall go quite, ſo that ye graunt the matter now to run,</l>
                        <l>To end with mirth emong us all, even as it was begun.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Say ye maſter vicar, &amp; he ſhall ſure confes to be your detter,</l>
                        <l>And all we that be here preſent, will lobe you much the better.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My part is the worſt, but ſince you all hereon agree,</l>
                        <l>Go even to maſter Baily, let it be ſo for me.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſaieſt thou diccon, art content th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ſhall on me depend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <p>Go to M. Baily, ſay on your mind, I know ye are my frend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then marke you well, to recompence this thy former action,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe thou haſt offended all, to make them ſatisfaction;</l>
                        <l>Before their faces here kneel down, and as I ſhall the teach,</l>
                        <l>For thou ſhalt take an othe of hodges leather breach,</l>
                        <l>Firſt for maſter Doctor, upon pain of his curſſe,</l>
                        <l>Where he will pay for al, thou never draw thy purſſe:</l>
                        <l>And when ye meet at one pot, he ſhall have the firſt pull,</l>
                        <l>And thou ſhalt never offer him the cup, but it be full.</l>
                        <l>To goodwife chat thou ſhalt be ſworn, even on the ſame wiſe,</l>
                        <l>If ſhe refuſe thy money once, never to offer it twiſe.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:49842:20"/>Thou ſhalt be bound by the ſame here, as thou doſt taken</l>
                        <l>When thou maiſt drinke of free coſt, thou never forſake it:</l>
                        <l>For gammer gurtons ſake, again ſworne ſhalt thou be.</l>
                        <l>To helpe hir to hir nedle again if it dolie in thee,</l>
                        <l>And likewiſe be bound, by the vertue of that</l>
                        <l>To be of good abering to Gib hir great Cat:</l>
                        <l>Laſt of all for Hodge, the othe to ſcanne,</l>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt never take him for fine gentleman.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hogd.</speaker>
                     <p>Come on fellow Diccon, chalbe even with thee now,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou wilt not ſticke to do this Diccon I trow,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No by my fathers ſkin, my hand down I lay it?</l>
                        <l>Loke as I have promiſed, I will not denay it,</l>
                        <l>But Hodge take good heed now, thou do not beſhite me.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>And gave him a good blow on the buttocks.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods hart thou falſe villain doſt thou bite me,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <p>What Hodge doth he hurt the or ever he begin?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He thruſt me into the buttocks, with a bodkin or a pin,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I</hi> ſay Gammer, Gammer?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>How now Hodge, how now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods malt Gammer gurtons.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art mad ich trow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you ſee the devil Gammer?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>The devil ſonne, god bleſſe us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Chould iche were hanged Gammer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Mary ſe ye might dreſſe us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Chaue it by the maſſe Gammer</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>What, not my néele Hodge?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Your neele Gammer, your néele.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>No fie, doſt but dodge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Cha found your neele Gammer, here in my hand be it</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>For all the lobes on earth Hodge, let me ſee it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hadg.</speaker>
                     <p>Soft Gammer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Hodge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Soft ich ſay, tarie a while.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay ſweet Hodge ſay truth, and not me begile.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <p>Cham ſure on it, ich warrant you, it goes no more aſtray</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Hodge when I ſpeak ſo fair: wil ſtill ſay me nay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Go near the light gammer, this well in faith good lucke:</l>
                        <l>Chwas almoſt undone: twas ſo far in my buttocke</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49842:21"/>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis mine own dear néele Hogde, ſikerly I wot,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                     <p>Cham <hi>I</hi> not a good ſonne gammer, cham <hi>I</hi> not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <p>Chriſt bleſſing light one thee, haſt made me for ever,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                     <p>Ich knew that ich muſt finde it, els chould a had it never.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By my troth goſſip gurton, I am even as glad,</l>
                        <l>As though I mine own ſelfe as good a turn had:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And I by my conſcience, to ſee it ſo cone forth,</l>
                        <l>Rejoyce ſo much at it as three nedles be worth.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
                     <p>I am no whit ſorry to ſee you ſo rejoyce,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor I much the glader for all this noice.</l>
                        <l>Yet ſay gramercie Diccon, for ſpringing of the game,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gramercie Diccon twentie times; o how glad cham.</l>
                        <l>If that chould do ſo much, your maſterdome to come hether,</l>
                        <l>Maſter Rat, goodwife Chat, and Diccon together:</l>
                        <l>Cha but one halfpeny, as far as iche know it,</l>
                        <l>And chil nor reſt this night till iche beſtow it.</l>
                        <l>If ever ye love me, let us go in and drinke,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I</hi> am content if the reſt thinke as <hi>I</hi> thinke.</l>
                        <l>Maſter Rat it ſhalbe beſt for you if we ſo do,</l>
                        <l>Then ſhall you warme you and dreſt your ſelfe too.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dic.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Soft ſirs, take us with you, the company ſhalbe the more,</l>
                        <l>As proude comes behinde they ſay, as anie goes before,</l>
                        <l>But now my good maſters ſince we muſt be gone,</l>
                        <l>And leave you behinde us, here all alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Since at our laſt ending, thus mery we be,</l>
                        <l>For Gammer Gurtons nedle ſake, let us have a plaudity.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49842:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
